# Katharina Duecker

I investigate how the temporal dynamics of the visual system support perception and attention. My hopthesis is that studying rhythmic and aperiodic dynamics can teach us how the brain allocates its computational resources efficiently. My main research tools are non-invasive brain recordings and computational modeling/machine learning.

### **EDUCATION**

#### NEUROSCIENCE & PSYCHOLOGY

2019 - 2023

**PhD in Neuroscience**, Centre For Human Brain Health, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, UK Supervisor: Prof Ole Jensen, Prof Kimron Shapiro

2016 - 2019

**MSc Neurocognitive Psychology**, Department of Psychology, Carl-von-Ossietzky University of Oldenburg, Germany Thesis: *Entrainment of Neuronal Gamma Oscillations using Rapid Frequency Tagging*Supervisor: Prof Christoph Herrmann, Grade: 1.2, Thesis: 1.0

2013 - 2016

**BSc Psychology**, Faculty of Psychology, Bielefeld University, Germany Thesis: *Attentional Capture by a Novel Stimulus in Visual Search* Supervisor: Prof Gernot Horstmann, Grade: 1.9, Thesis: 1.0

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### **DOCTORAL RESEARCH**

#### Synchronizing endogenous neuronal oscillations using photic stimulation [1]

Rhythmic responses to photic stimulation are often assumed to reflect a synchronization of ongoing neuronal oscillations to the non-invasive stimulus. My research challenges this view, showing that the intrinsic dynamics of the brain are not easily perturbed. This study motivates further work to understand how rhythmic sensory stimulation affects cellular activity.

### Investigating the neuronal substrates of Visual Search (poster)

Visual search is a classic experiment used to operationalize selective attention to visual objects. This project aims to uncover the neural substrates of numerous behavioral findings and their corresponding models. I use Magnetoencephalography and rapid photic stimulation to investigate how the visual cortex modulates its neuronal excitability to solve the search task.

#### Biologically plausible neuronal dynamics in Computer Vision (see abstract 7)

This project is motivated by the idea that the dynamics of neuronal activity prevent sensory systems from getting overwhelmed by the abundance of stimuli competing for our attention. This modeling work shows that implementing biologically plausible temporal dynamics in a Machine Learning algorithm solves the competition between multiple stimuli, and allows the system to process them in rapid succession.

#### **INTERNSHIPS & STUDENT PROJECTS**

Nov 2017 – Apr 2018

**Electric field modeling of transcranial brain stimulation [2]**, Prof Christoph Herrmann, Dr Florian Kasten Carl-von-Ossietzky University of Oldenburg, Department of Psychology, Germany

Aug 2017 – Nov 2017

**Decision-making in pathological gambing using fMRI** [3], Dr Alexander Genauck, Prof Nina Romanczuk-Seiferth Charité Berlin, Department of Psychiatry & Psychotherapy, Germany

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Grading: 1.0 - 1.7: very good, 1.7 - 2.7: good, 2.7 - 3.7: pass, >4: fail

### **SKILLS**

Programming Other

MATLAB Psychtoolbox, fieldtrip Languages German, English, Spanish, French

Python NumPy, SciPy, MNE, PyTorch, Keras Other Digital Signal Processing, Dynamic Systems

Matplotlib, jupyter notebook, spyder Theory, Computational Neuroscience,

R ggplot, lme4, ez Eyetracking

other shell (bash) & ETEX

### **GRANTS & AWARDS**

Jun 2022

Travel Grant, Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds

3,150 EUR/ 3,307.5 USD

May 2022

Howard Hughs Medical Award, CSHL course waiver

1,500 USD

Mar 2022

PhD paper of the year 2022(2nd place), Centre for Human Brain Health

Oct 2021

Leading Women in Neuro-AI abstract award, Montreal AI & Neuroscience meeting

400 CAD/ 324 USD

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] K. Duecker, T. P. Gutteling, C. S. Herrmann, and O. Jensen, "No evidence for entrainment: Endogenous gamma oscillations and rhythmic flicker responses coexist in visual cortex," *Journal of Neuroscience*, 2021. DOI: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3134-20.2021.
- [2] F. H. Kasten, K. Duecker, M. C. Maack, A. Meiser, and C. S. Herrmann, "Integrating electric field modeling and neuroimaging to explain inter-individual variability of tacs effects," *Nature Communications*, 2019. DOI: 10.1038/s41467-019-13417-6.
- [3] A. Genauck, C. Matthis, M. Andrejevic, et al., "Neural correlates of cue-induced changes in decision-making distinguish subjects with gambling disorder from healthy controls," Addiction Biology, 2021. DOI: 10.1111/adb.12951.
- [4] A. Zhigalov, K. Duecker, and O. Jensen, "The visual cortex produces gamma band echo in response to broadband visual flicker," *PLoS Computational Biology*, 2021. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009046.

## **CONFERENCE ABSTRACTS/TALKS**

- [5] K. Duecker, K. L. Shapiro, S. Hanslmayr, J. Wolfe, Y. Pan, and O. Jensen, "Guided search is associated with modulated neuronal excitability to target and distractor features in early visual regions," International Conference of Cognitive Neuroscience (Poster), May 2022.
- [6] K. Duecker, M. Idiart, and O. Jensen, "Space-to-time-conversion: Oscillations in an artificial neural network generate a temporal code representing simultaneous visual inputs," Montreal AI & Neuroscience (Graphical Abstract), Nov. 2021.
- [7] K. Duecker, "Oscillatory responses to sinusoidal and broadband frequency tagging: No entrainment, but a perceptual echo in the gamma-band," Neuoxillations: Early career researcher talk series by the Experimental Psychology group, University of Oxford (invited talk), Sep. 2021.
- [8] K. Duecker, "Early career researcher talk: How does the visual system implement selective attention?" Psyched@UoB (Invited talk), Jun. 2021.
- [9] K. Duecker, T. P. Gutteling, C. S. Herrmann, and O. Jensen, "No evidence for entrainment: Endogenous gamma oscillations and rhythmic flicker responses coexist in visual cortex," Neuromatch Conference 3 (Virtual poster), Nov. 2020.
- [10] K. Duecker, T. P. Gutteling, C. S. Herrmann, and O. Jensen, "Does rapid frequency tagging entrain neuronal gamma oscillations?" British Association for Cognitive Neuroscience (Poster), Sep. 2019.

# **SUMMER SCHOOLS, MACHINE LEARNING & MATHEMATICS**

Jul 2022 Computational Neuroscience: Vision, Summer School at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Long Island, NY, USA

Jun 2022

Kavli Summer Institue in Cognitive Neuroscience, Summer School at UC Santa Barbara, California, USA

Neuromatch Academy: Deep Learning, (online summer school)

Jul 2021

Neuromatch Academy: Computational Neuroscience, (online summer school)

Jul 2020

Linear Algebra for Neuroscientists, Summer School at Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands

Aug 2019

Machine Learning I: Unsupervised Learning, M.Sc. Physics course at the University of Oldenburg, Germany

2018/019

Tools for Teaching Quantitative Thinking, Erasmus+ Seminar at the University of Graz

2017

### TEACHING/MENTORING

# Mentoring

2022

Jiahui An, M.Sc. Cognitive Neuroscience and Robotics: Brain-Computer Interface based on photic stimulation

#### TEACHING (M.Sc. LEVEL, SELECTED)

Autumn 2022

MEG practical, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham

8 hours lecture + flexible tutoring, 3 students; developed and taught an introductory course on MEG with applications in MATLAB

Spring 2020, 2021, 2022

**Application of Electrophysiological Approaches**, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham 20 hours teaching/tutoring per term, grading of assignments, 40 students

Spring 2020, 2021

**MATLAB programming**, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham 10 hours teaching/tutoring per term, 40 students

Winter 2018/2019

**Fundamental competencies in Psychology**, Department of Computer Science, University of Oldenburg 20 hours teaching, weekly seminar on fundamental literature in cognitive psychology, prepared and taught teaching material, 10 students

Winter 2017/2018

Multivariate Statistics, Department of Psychology, University of Oldenburg

20 hours teaching, weekly tutorial on mutlivariate statistics, prepared repetition of weekly lectures and applications in R, 35 students

## AD HOC PEER-REVIEWING

Journal of Neuroscience; Psychophysiology; European Journal of Neuroscience; Cerebral Cortex; PLOS One; Brain & Behavior; Attention, Perception, & Psychophysics